<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A wounderfull prophecie or pronosticatio[n] begynnynge from the yere of oure Lorde M.D.XXXI. to the lawde and prayse of the moost victoryous Emperowre Charles the fyfthe of that name borne within the triumpha[n]t towne of Gandt, in the golden yere .M.D. vppo[n] the .xxiiij. daye of February, whiche daye is neyther named nor no[m]bred, because it was in the leapeyere pronostycate by Master Salomon the Jewe, [and] physician greatly soundynge to the honour of God and lawde of the famous towne of Gandt.</title>
            <author>Salomon, Dr., of Ruhrmond.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1543</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106795</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842505</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842505</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11370)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 448:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A wounderfull prophecie or pronosticatio[n] begynnynge from the yere of oure Lorde M.D.XXXI. to the lawde and prayse of the moost victoryous Emperowre Charles the fyfthe of that name borne within the triumpha[n]t towne of Gandt, in the golden yere .M.D. vppo[n] the .xxiiij. daye of February, whiche daye is neyther named nor no[m]bred, because it was in the leapeyere pronostycate by Master Salomon the Jewe, [and] physician greatly soundynge to the honour of God and lawde of the famous towne of Gandt.</title>
                  <author>Salomon, Dr., of Ruhrmond.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Widow of C. Ruremond,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Antwerp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1543]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>End of text dated May 1543--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A wounderfull Prophecie or pronoſticatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begynnynge from the yere of oure Lorde M.D.XXXI. to the lawde and prayſe of the mooſt victoryous Emperowre Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the fyfthe of that name / borne within the triumpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t towne of Gandt / in the golden yere. M.D. vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xxiiij. daye of February / whiche daye is neyther named nor no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was in the leape yere Pronoſtycate by Maſter Salomon the Iewe / &amp; Phyſician greatly ſoundynge to the honour of God and lawde of the famous towne of Gandt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:7167:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The prologe.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. i.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmoche as the feare of god is the begynnynge of wyſedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / <note place="margin">Iaco. i.</note> And that euery good and parfett gyfte / is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue / to as manye as aſke it in faithe / according to the ſayinge of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. I therfore (hauynge thys feare of the Lorde before myn eyes) deſyre of him / tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe hys allmyghtye power and endeles mercye / to derecte my penne a ryght / that thys my lytell laboure and worke / maye ſo procede (accordyng to his mooſt godly will and pleaſure) that I in no wyſe erre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ryght waye of truethe. For I haue here ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hande (throughe Gods permiſſyon) to pronoſticate / of the very zeale and loue / whyche I beare vnto the trueth. Takynge my grounde and foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / oute of the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecyes of Eſay / Iermy / Ezechiel / Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras / with diuers other / not omit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng that pryncely prophet Dauid / lyke as I haue done three yeres paſte / but I entende not to paſſe ouer ſo lyghtlye.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prognostication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7167:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſt we ſaye / throughe the mouthe of the ꝓphet Eſdras.<note place="margin">Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of ſin Aſia is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the .iij. parte of the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lde ſtret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theaſt / vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypte. Egipte ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the whole worlde ſo that i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecye I do as well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes as xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ians.</note> Wo be vnto the o Babilon and Aſia / wo be vnto the o Egypte &amp; Syria: gyrde yowre ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues wyth clothes of ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke &amp; heare / &amp; moorne for youre chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / be ſory (I ſaye) for youre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruccion is at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. A ſwerde is ſent vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you / &amp; who wyl torne it backe? A fyre is kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deled agaynſt you / of the fearce vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God / and who wyl que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tche it? Beholde ſayeth the prophet. They take the worde of God but for a ſcorne / and haue no luſte ther vnto. Therfore I am (ſayth he) ſo ful of thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne indignacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Oh Lorde / that I may ſuffer it no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. For fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leaſte vnto the moſt they hange &amp; depende all vppon couetuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prophet vnto the preſte / they go all about with falſhead &amp; lyes. Agayne / ſaith Eſdras / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men ſhal thynke to haue peace vnytie and concorde / &amp; that all maner of vittaylles ſhall be habondaunt / &amp; ſo good cheape vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth / that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall thynke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be in good caſe / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then ſhall the great myſchefe &amp; vengeaunce of the Lorde falle vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / with warres / death / dearthe
<pb facs="tcp:7167:3"/> peſtylences and great diſquyetnes / whiche are but the begynnyng of moornyngis and ſorrowes / In ſomoche that the people ſhall tremble for feare / <note place="margin">Ioel. ij.</note> ſayinge nowe the Lorde commeth &amp; is harde at hande / A darke daye a gloomynge daye / a clowdye daye / a ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my daye ſhall appeare.<note place="margin">Amos. viij.</note> The ſonges of the people ſhall be turned to ſorowe / Soche a honger will I ſende vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earthe (ſayth the Lorde) that no man ſhall be able to ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe it / in ſoche a maner that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may well ſaye / <note place="margin">Pſal. c.xxxviij.</note> where ſhall I hyde me from the wrath of God? yea they ſhall ſaye (ſyttinge by the waters of Babilon and weape) we will ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge our harpes vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trees that are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in / as oft as we remembre Syon. For who eſcape the warre / ſhall fele the plage of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence / and he that is quyte of the one / ſhal not eſcape the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of the other. And ſoche ſmall loue ſhall theyre be / that one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall fynde no maner of comforte at the hande of an other. Lett no man merueyll at theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that be to come / ſeynge they ſhalbe ſent of God as ſcourges for the puniſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſynne.<note place="margin">S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nardes ſaying.</note> S. Bernarde (as it were in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chryſt) ſayethe. O thowe man tell me the cauſe af thy myſfortune and chaunce whiche thowe haſte in thy goodes / bodye / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7167:3"/> ſoule / Thow ſerueſt the deuell / and not me He hathe not created &amp; made the of nought / neyther hath he ſaued the / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thowe waſt loſte / Chryſt him ſelfe dyd not redeme the with the ſonne / moone / ſterres and plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / but with his precyous bloude through deathe. Therfore ſaythe the prophet Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye / I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrayned to make my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnt vppon yowe / and vppon yowre chyldren.<note place="margin">Iere. ij.</note> Oh ye curſed ſynners / howe wofull a thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge will it be vnto yowe / whiche haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the trewe God / fallynge to ſynne / the deuell and all vanyties. What vnfaythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes haue yowe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in me / ſaithe the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / yowr owne conſcience ſhall accuſe you / and yowr own wickednes ſhal condempne yow. Agayne we ſpeake vnto yow / throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe the mouthe of the ꝓphet Eſaye.<note place="margin">Eſay. i.</note> Heare oh heauen / harken O earthe / for the Lorde ſpeaketh / I haue nouryſſhed and broughte vp chyldren / and thei are fallen away from me. An oxe knoweth his owner / and an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe his maſters ſtable / but my people knowe me not. Expert they be in blaſphemies / falſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hed / and lyes / mooſt lyke a frowarde gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and vnnaturall chyldren / as it apea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euydently ynoughe / with what othes they blaſphemye God / in euerye place / as
<pb facs="tcp:7167:4"/> at weddynges / maryages / banckettes / fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes / tauernes / markettes / &amp; in many other paſtymes / playes / games / and ſoche other thynges / that by ſoche deuyllyſſhnes the deuyne name of God is openly detracted / ſclaundered &amp; blaſphemed. Yea in ſo moche that it is ſo derided &amp; mocked withall / none other wyſe / then as men ſhulde eyther put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te oute their lyppes or poynt it withe their formuſt fynger / with ſoche dyſhoneſtie and abhomynable vyces and ſynnes / whiche at this tyme I ſhame to rehearce / ſo that ther be at this preſent daye / many more people lyuynge beaſtelye &amp; fylthelye / then ſoberly honeſtly or vertuouſly. It neadeth no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacyon of ſcripture / ſeynge the actes be to manyfeſt as wel to the rulers temporall as ſpirituall. In ſo moche that the confeſſyon of fayth / true repentaunce / and godly Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes with the pure preachinge of the Goſpell / is ſo moche neglected &amp; diſpyſed / that me thynke it is greatly to be lamented that it is ſo longe vnpunyſſhed / for dyſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie withe dyſobedience is ſo greatly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred to ſoche maner of vnſhamefaſte bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denes / that in a maner it is to late to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. And it is to be feared that there be many ſturdy vylleynes / vnder the coloure
<pb facs="tcp:7167:4"/> and pretence of beggynge / wyll do moche more harme / than eyther Iewes / Turkes / Agarenes or any maner of kynde of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers / ſo that they wyll not onely be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent / to begge in the open and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men ſtreates of townes and Cyties / as do the lame / dome / and crepell / nor yet to ſtande at the churche doores &amp; porches / but withoute any ſhame wyll entre boldelye into me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes houſes and tauernes. And ſome there be of the other partie / that appere to the people lame / halt and no leſſe then crepell in dede / that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute the townes and Cyties / in the feldes will take them to their fete / layinge awaye their cruches / ſome tyme vppon their ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders / moch more redyer to take a purſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently / then to aſke for Chriſtus ſake chary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tablye. Thus ſee yowe two maner of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers / bothe worthely to be reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and amended. For whan the one kynde of them hathe before none / brought home their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uender / and fylled not onelye their bellyes full / but euen cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med them vp to the thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / yet muſt they agayne at after none / ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke agayne in the ſtreates / where they maye haue their bagges full agaynſt the next da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye / ſo that they go gulpyng lyke brute bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes / neuer ſatiſfyed. The other ſorte bolle
<pb facs="tcp:7167:5"/> &amp; ſwyll all that euer they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gett. The lorde which ſeeth from aboue / and knoweth that all theſe thynges are trewe / ſhall ones iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that theſe be euen the ſhepe withoute wolle. Althoughe there is no man that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hede of them / yet is it not ſuffycyent that both theis kyndes of people lyue thus myſerablye ydelly and wredchedlye / from whome commeth ſkante one good woorde oute of their mouthes. And it is not a lytle to be maruayled at / that theſe enormyties be vnpunyſſhed / ſeynge they ſo great and intollerable. But euen lyke as the lynke of one chayne draweth after hym an other / ſo dothe one myſchefe and ſynne drawe an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after hym. For ther is no great ſynne that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth alone / but draweth by certeyn occaſyons many other euelles after hym / by the whyche the great indignacyon from the Lorde / is caſte as a plage to come vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dyſobedyent / of whome the Prophet Dauid ſpeaketh. They reioyce when they do euell / hauyng delyte and pleaſure in theyre euell dedes. For the wycked when he commeth into the daunger and deapthe of ſynne / he paſſeth nothyng at all for it / ſo that.<note place="margin">Rom. i.</note> S. Paull ſayeth / that God hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all ſoche people vp into theyre hartes
<pb facs="tcp:7167:5"/> luſtes / and vnto all lewde mynde to do ſoch thynges whiche be not comely / beyng full of all vnryghtuous doynges / folowynge the foote paithes and ſteppes of Caym and Iudas / with that ſtyfnecked &amp; ſtony harted Pharo. Notwithſtandynge the goodnes &amp; great lyberalyte of God forgeueth the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner ſo ofte as he falleth / to the intent he ſhulde repent &amp; amende. Therfore nowe ye Chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aryſe from youre ſynnes / and open youre eares &amp; vnderſtand with youre hartes the wordes of the Prophet / whiche ſayeth. I am ſo full of thy indygnation.<note place="margin">Iere. vi</note> O Lorde / that I can ſuffre it no lenger. They take thy worde but for a ſcorne / tredinge it vnder their fete / hauyng no luſte thervnto. Powre out thy wrath vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are without thy worde / that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pryſoner with the wyſe / the aged with the crepell. For what with the intollerable burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſcrybes &amp; pharizees / the inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable &amp; beaſtly deſyres of the adulters &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicatours / with the vnmeaſurable couetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes / falſehead / frawde &amp; deceyte of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers &amp; ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſortes of people / the churche is become (I feare me) a very denne of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues robbers &amp; bloudy murtherers. Therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſayth the Lord by hys Prophet / vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all
<pb facs="tcp:7167:6"/> ſoche ſhall rayne ſolphur / fyre &amp; brymſtone with wyndes bothe troublous and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtious and all other plages / no leſſe then it was ſene vppon Sodoma and Gomorra.<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>Geneſ</abbr> xix. Ezechi. xvi. Iere. vi Eſa. xxi Ezechi. xxxviij. Pſalm. xcviij.</note> And agayn ſpeakith the Lorde by the mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the of his prophet Eſaye. I will powre out vppon yowe (ſaythe he) my wrathe / and I will caſte downe vppon yow the fyre of my vengeaunce and indignation / withe thon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der / lyghteninge / hayle and darkenes. So that there ſhall go a fyre before the Lorde / whiche ſhall conſume and burne vp his eny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myes on euery ſyde. Therfore clothe yowr ſelfes with ſacke clothe / caſte aſſhes vppon yowre heades / faſte and praye / lament and repente yowe of yowre ſynfull lyuynge.<note place="margin">Ionas. iij.</note> For the dayes of the Lorde are at hande / ſo that euerye thynge whiche hathe bene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyed ſhalbe fulfylled.<note place="margin">Ezechi. xij.</note> Remembre what great pytie and mercy / the Lorde had ouer the Niniuytes / after that they withe longe lamentation / repentaunce and feruent ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicacyon / ſubmitted them ſelues wholy to hym. Alſo not withſtandinge that theſe .iij. men / Moyſes Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Samuel / offended agaynſte the Lorde / yet when they repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and prayed hertelye / the Lorde hearde them / yet puniſſhed he their tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſions / 
<pb facs="tcp:7167:6"/> as it appeareth by Moyſes whiche ſynned at the water of Stryfe / by reaſon wherof he myghte not entre into the lande of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys.<note place="margin">Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. ij.</note> Lykewyſe when Aaron made a golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calfe vnto the lordes people.<note place="margin">Exodi. xxxij. i. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viij. cha</note> And Samuel ſynned beynge neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in teaching of his chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yf God haue not ſpared ſoche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / we then ought to take good hede / howe we walke in the p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſence of God. Therfore ſayth the prophet / beware of the plage / and peſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence of darkenes / which is a ſyckenes that dyſtroyeth the lyght of the daye. And if ye will not turne and amende / then the dayes of ſorrowe ſhall ſodenly come / from whoſe face thowe ſhalt not flee.<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>Geneſ</abbr> vij. Pſal. ij.</note> Thowe ſhalte call vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the flowdes of the waters / with the hyghenes of the mountaynes to hyde the. There ſhalbe ſoche a cryinge and waylyng amongeſt the chryſtians / that the one ſhall ſaye to the other / it were good that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had bene borne. Inſomoche that ſome ſhall dyſdayne the wordes of this prophet / yet is there nothyng more truer / then that whiche is ſpoken of before. So that greate heauynes and ſorowes ſhall chaunce / aſwel vppon other ſtaungers and alyaunt nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as vppon the dowche lande / wherfore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houethe me ſome thynge to ſpeake therof / 
<pb facs="tcp:7167:7"/> that men perceauynge the lytle ſhyppe of Peter (throughe diſcorde and diſobedience) to be rent and broken in peces / agaynſt the harde ſtony rockes / ſhall then the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyer ſee theſe thinges to be true &amp; no fables And thoughe ther be many whiche thynke the naturall inclinacions of the elementes to be but fantaſticall and worthy of no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyte / yet can they not but graunt the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of God to be vnfallable / in as moch as it procedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the boſome of the father. And here do I bothe earneſtly and playnly admonyſſhe the Germanies bothe hyghe &amp; lowe to ioyne them ſelues vnto the Egle / For elles there ſhall aryſe amongeſt them / ſoche warre &amp; diſcorde that it ſhal not eaſely be apeaced. For the Turke ſhall with great violence go about to deſtroye the landes of Meyſſen / Duryngen &amp; Heſſe / as Merlyn dothe ꝓphecye / whiche ſayth by ſoche mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the Emperours maieſtye myght come to ſome myſfortune of hys body / by reaſon of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction of Iouis beynge in Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio. Alſo other princes &amp; lordes of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne Empyre / ſhalbe ſome thynge trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled of their ſubiectes / notwithſtandinge it ſhall not longe contynewe. And after that the Emperours maieſtie hathe taken great
<pb facs="tcp:7167:7"/> payne &amp; trouble in trauaylinge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey to an other / with moche diſquietnes &amp; ſmall reſte / aſwell by lande as by ſea / then ſhall the ſpyrituall ſwerde not be ſo longe / <note place="margin">The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall ſwerde ſhall be made ſhorter.</note> ſo brode / nor yet ſo ſharpe / to cut with ſoche viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as it hath done in tymes paſte. And in thys tyme ſhall the ſonne loſe hyr lyght .iij. poyntes and a halfe great / which ſhalbe vppon a Frydaye after. S. Bartholemews daye at one of the clocke in the after none or ther vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / becauſe Leo hauinge the aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent / ſignifyeth to vs many fearful warres &amp; great ſhedinge of bloude. Whiche as wel they of the lande of Auſtriche ſhal perceaue and feale as many other ſtraunge nacions.<note place="margin">Auſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ys vnder the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do kyng of Ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gary</note> For Merlyn ſayeth that the Turke wythe great power purpoſeth to deſtroye the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re named landes of Meyſſen / Duringen and Heſſe. Therfore let not this Godly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſſion and plage / whiche hangeth ouer youre heades (good Chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) be forgot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten / but rather let it be cloſed within youre hartes / ſeynge it is none other wyſe lyke / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to come to paſſe. For as truely as the Lorde lyueth / great ſorowes &amp; troubles are at hande in whiche the holy prophecies ſhal be fulfylled / and the true Chriſten churche ſhall ſore decaye / euen lyke as it chaunced
<pb facs="tcp:7167:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnto the congregacyons of the Iewes / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge in great proſperytie / felycytie &amp; pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / Hearynge the wounderfull thynges wroughte aboue in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / perceyuyng one lyke a vallyaunt Captayne / beyng in a fye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry charret and ſyttyng in a ſtoole of golde / hauinge in his hande a ſharpe ſpeare / and a voice hearde in the entrynge in of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / which ſayed within a very ſhorte tyme we will depart hence / which ſygnifyed the mercye of God to be withdrawen from the generacyon of the Iewes / and it ſo came to paſſe / as it appered mooſte manyfeſtlye by the diſtruccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / all this not with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandinge nor nothynge at all regardynge theſe viſyons thei mocked and derided the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as thinges mooſte falſe and vntrue. And I feare me that as many of the dowchelande / dothe eſteyme and iuge theſe admonicyons of the prophetes as fables / euen ſo dothe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther landes and nacions / whiche will neuer repente / vntill the tyme that thoſe thinges happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as did to the Iewes for theyr diſſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.<note place="margin">Apoca. xviij. Eſa. xij</note> But heare what S. Ihon ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the apocalips / of them whiche ioyne them ſelues vnto the Babilonical ſtrompet Babilon that great cytie is fallen / whiche hathe poyſoned all nacions / cauſyng them
<pb facs="tcp:7167:8"/> to dryncke of the wyne of her ſtinking for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicacion.<note place="margin">Iere. li.</note> That myghty and great cytie Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilon (ſayeth he) is falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and become the ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bitacyon of deuels. And why? bycauſe the Kinges of the earthe haue committed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicacion with her.<note place="margin">Apoco. xiiij.</note> And her marchantes are waxen ryche with the haboundaunce of her pleaſures / yet in one houre (o thou Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) is thy iugement come.<note place="margin">Eſaie. xiij. Ieremy xiiij. Ezechi. xxxiiij.</note> Thy ſheaperdes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue diſtroyed and ſcatered my flocke a brode ſayeth the Lorde / feadinge them ſelues / and not my people. Therfore (ſayeth he) I will vpon them / and requyer my ſhepe oute of theyr handes / &amp; will feade them myn owne ſelfe. For howe manye is there at this daye which for the inwarde zeale which thei bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vnto the heade of that cytie of Babilon / take an occaſyon (after the enſample of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod) to make inquiſycion for fylthye lucres ſake / <note place="margin">Mat. i.</note> for the pore innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lambes of Chryſt neuer leauing of vntill thei haue ſhed their bloude / thynkinge therby their lordeſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and Kyngdomes lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to endure. And it is ſeine at this preſente daye in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / that althoughe the name of the heade of the Babilonicall cytie be aboliſhed / yet were his lawes neuer more auaunced / nor his miniſters and adherentes had in more
<pb facs="tcp:7167:9"/> hygher eſtimacion. I wolde there were ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me man that coulde make the ſpiritualty to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de this leſſon of Chriſte wel / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re he ſaieth / <note place="margin">mat. xx.</note> that the Princes and Lordes of the heathen / haue power ouer the heathen people / but it ſhulde not be ſo amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt his diſciples / Nowe then / if they wolde harken to this doctryne / and graunte them ſelues to be Chriſtes diſciples / then can they not loke to haue ſoche rule in the worlde / ouer Dukedomes / Erledomes / Cyties and tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / in ſoche ample wiſe / that worldly prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces / in a maner be nothyng to be compared vnto them / or at the leaſte withoute them. I ſpeake not this in diſprayſe of the ſupery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our powers / for eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame Goſpel whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che taketh worldelye promocion from the ſpirituall powers / dothe agayn reſtore the ſame to the Ciuyle Maieſtrates / the which oughte to be obeyed as well of the ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie / <note place="margin">Roma. xiij.</note> as of the temperaltye / ſeinge it is thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denaunces of God him ſelfe / for the puniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemente of them that be euell / and mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyninge of the good. So that who ſo euer withſtandeth them / withſtandeth the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of god / ſeinge thei be his myniſtres for oure wealthe and profyt / vnder whoſe ſubiection / God hathe inſtituted all creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.
<pb facs="tcp:7167:9"/> For he ſayeth clerely / Omnis anima / here is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excepted / nether ſpiritual nor te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall.<note place="margin">Roma. xiij.</note> For where this order is not in the church of Chriſte / there muſte the Lorde ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſende downe his plages and puniſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / accordinge to the prophecie of Hyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degardus / whiche ſayeth / the time ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / that the moone ſhall loſe her light / that is to ſaye .iiij. poyntes / whiche ſhalbe apon a monday after vincula Petri / at .xij. of the clocke at mydnighte / the aſcendent beinge in Aquario .xviij. degrees in Libra / whiche vndoutedly dothe ſignify vnto vs / that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny godly ordenaunces and ſtatutes / which haue bene made for the ſetting forwarde of gods honour and the publyke wealth / ſhall be diſanulled and broken / and other wicked and vngodlye actes ſhalbe put in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For in this time ſhall ſtande vp a falſe prophet / whiche ſhall go aboute to diſtroye the cheifeſt articles of our faithe and beleif / and ſo throughe an vtwarde and gloryous appearaunce / he ſhall ſeduce moche people / and worke many ſtraunge thinges. And in this time ſhall the Emperowrs maieſtie be vexed and troubled with many of his ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis / ſo that the priſons in euery place whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re men do vſe to execute iuſtice / ſhalbe fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:7167:10"/>
/ with monkes / fryres / no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes and ſoche other / ſo that thei ſhal lyue in an vncerteyn and vnſure eſtate. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; artify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers / ſhall not greatly profyt in their affay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / but that ſhall not longe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynewe. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> women ſhall haue good fortune in their tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaylle &amp; labour / for they ſhall brynge forth many chyldren within ſhorte tyme. After this ſhal ther be two eclipſis / the one of the Sonne / the other of the moone. The ſonne ſhall be darkened .vi. poyntes great fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnynge to the endynge / which ſhalbe vppon a wedneſdaye .viij. dayes after the .xij. day at after none. And agayne the moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſhal looſe hyr lyght vppon a frydaye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the conuerſyon of. S. Paull in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge at twoo of the clocke in the .ix. degre of Leo / whiche betokeneth great miſchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and fortune to them that dwelle vppon the ſea coaſtes / or where the grounde is lowe. In thys tyme men ſhall ſee a great fall and decaye of Turkes / ſo that the empyre ſhall haue great rule &amp; domynion / conquerynge diuers la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; lordeſhips. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the nobles of the empyre ſhall haue proſperous ſucceſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and fortune with great fauoure of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes. In the mean tyme ſhal the ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be at variaunce / ſtrife / &amp; diſcorde / for the
<pb facs="tcp:7167:10"/> promocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and goodes of the churche. And while thei are thus ſtriuinge one agaynſte an other / marchauntes and all other arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers / ſhall haue more proſperous and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lucke in their trades &amp; buſines then thei had before. Notwithſtanding / Italye / Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way / and Denmark ſhalbe vexed troubled and be brought to great heauines. Aboute this tyme ſhall there be in Fraunce / in the lande of Luke / and in ſome places of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of Cleue / great peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and other ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge diſeaſes / then ſhal the flowdes of the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of Ryne braſte forth with great viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / and ouerflowe dyuers partes of the lande / to the greate diſcomoditie of the people. In this tyme ſhal the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne be darkned .ix. poyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes from benethe vpwarde / vppon the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de friday after Eaſter after none at .iiij. of the clocke .xij. degrees in the ſygne of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſces / ſo that then thaſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal ſhowe him ſelfe ſignifying vnto vs / that there ſhall be a great nombre of princes depoſed / ſo that the crowne of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of Boheme ſhal ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d voide / through the great diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſubiectes. And becauſe thei do reproue the rodde wherwith thei ſhulde be beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / I wil therfore (ſaithe the Lorde) viſite their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion and diſobedience / <note place="margin">Amos. viij.</note> withe a ſharper
<pb facs="tcp:7167:11"/> rodde / that is / with the ſwerde of warre pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtilence dearthe and deathe. Then ſhall the p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lates of the churche be at ſtrife / one agayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte an other for diuers cauſes / whiche I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende not moche to entreat of at this tyme / but will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte the thinges vnto god / yet will not I ouer ſlyppe the wordes of that princely prophet Dauid / which ſaithe.<note place="margin">Pſal. ij.</note> The kinges of the earth ſhall ſtande vp / and the rulers ſhall counſell and come to gether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the Lorde / and his anoynted. For bothe Pilate and Herode / Annas and Cay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phas / ſcribes &amp; phariſees / whiche ſeke their own profet and aduauntage / with no ſmall diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and diſcorde / ſekyng the ſoules of them / <note place="margin">Eſaye. xiij.</note> which (the prophet Eſay ſayeth) ſhal not yet dye / Thei ſhall right well perceaue the great plages of god / withe lamentinge and moorninge as la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes with oute oyle / &amp; lanternes with out light / beinge both idle / blinde &amp; vayn.<note place="margin">Pſalm. lxi.</note> For yf thei were layd agayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte vanitie in a peire of balaunce / thei ſhuld flye vp vnto the ſkye / and be moche lighter then euen vanitye it ſelfe. Harken therfore (ſayeth the Lorde) ye princes of Sodoma / &amp; ye people of Gomorra / theſe my wordes. For the ſynne of my people / I will (ſayeth he) ſuffer ypocrites to raigne ouer you. Let
<pb facs="tcp:7167:11"/> vs take hede of the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull example whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re the aungell af god did deſtroye apon one nighte in the pauillio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s .C.lxxxv. thouſande me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">iiij. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xix. Eſaie. xxxvij.</note> For vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly theſe plages that are to come / ſhall be for the ſynnes / whiche raygne at this daye in the worlde / ſo that there ſhal aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether in one felde / many nobles of greate power / whiche willingly ſhal go to battell / where moche bloude ſhall be ſhedde / moſte eſpecially of the wicked / in ſoche wyſe that the thirde parte of the worlde / ſhal there be ſlayne.<note place="margin">iiij. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras. xv</note> For I will holde my tonge no len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger (ſayeth the Lorde) ſeinge the people be ſo wicked a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vngodly / for the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the troubled / criethe vnto me / and the ſoules of the ryghtuous complayne conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually / therfore will I aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the bloude of my people / ſo that the worlde ſhalbe full of wofulnes and miſery. The grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſhall lye voide / and not be tilled / the trees ſhall bear frute and ſhall not be gathered. The corne that is ſowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the feldes / ſhall not be brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte home into the barnes / the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall weape and wayle / for the loſſe of their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes / that ſhall periſſhe withe the power of the ſwerde. And more ouer / Aloufreſant prophecyethe / that in this tyme / the trewe
<pb facs="tcp:7167:12"/> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhall haue moche perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles &amp; ſorowes / for the worde of God. And after that ſhall there folowe great dearthe / and deathe / as well in other places / as in douchelande. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ther come in the coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of Europe / ſoche rayne / wynde &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt / that many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall be ſlayne therwith And this tempeſte ſhal come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the north / ſo that many ſhall go at nyghts merely to theyre beddes / whiche ſhalbe founde dead in the mornynge / and thus ended hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie. In this tyme alſo ſhall the papiſtrie and ſeate of Rome ſtande voyde / ſo that the Emperour ſhall take vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to ordeyne and inſtytute an other in the ſame ſeate / to whome the Emperoure ſhall adioyne hym ſelfe &amp; make attoneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the churche. And the man whome he ſhall thus ordeyne / ſhal be of great worthynes &amp; vertue / and therto be ſett lyke one of power: ſo that after that he ſhall put downe / &amp; take awaye great poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſyons / rentes / promocions &amp; dignyties / from the prelates and prebendaries / forbyd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge all outwarde vayne glorious pompe and pryde / aſwell in externall lyghtnes of rayme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; apparell bothe of men &amp; women / as alſo the ſuperfluytie of Golde / Syluer / pearles / precious ſtones / and ſoche lyke / ſo
<pb facs="tcp:7167:12"/> that he ſhall wyll euery man &amp; woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to their vocacyon and callyng to go ſoberly apparelled / as it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the true membres of Chriſt. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt to be preached / throughe oute all the worlde / rebukyng all ſynfull &amp; vicious lyuinge of the people but he ſhall not longe contynewe. Aboute this tyme ſhal ther be hearde of a great fall and deſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Turkes / amongeſt whom ther ſhal be a great inſurreccion / by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherof thei ſhalbe troubled with moche myſerie &amp; calamitie. For the ſtyrringe vp of Saturnus ſhall worke wounderſly wythe them / to their great myſfortune &amp; chaunce / ſo that the Turke ſhall haue but lytell cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and comforte to make warre agaynſt the chriſtians. The ſpyritualtie agayne on the other partie / ſhalbe at no ſmall variau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and dyſcorde amongeſt them ſelues / by the reaſon wherof many Kynges and prynces ſhall take good occaſyon to reforme many enormyties / lytle to their eaſe and proffyt. For many of them whiche thynke to buyld vppon a foundacyon as hard as any rocke / ſhall fynde that it is but a very ſlypperiſhe ſande. Nowe if me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of power and renowne / wyll buylde vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe foundacions ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne
<pb facs="tcp:7167:13"/> and vnſure / yt ys no marueyll / thoughe God do plage them for their wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes / that ſo wylfully reſyſte and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge at all regarde theſe his godly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſions / whiche ſhulde moue and ſterre all chriſten men to repentaunce. O Lorde how ſhorte is the time of mercy / and howe feaw be there that require it at thy handes in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / which thinge obteyned / we ſhal euer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue / and neuer dye?<note place="margin">Math. xv.</note> The woman of canane / called to Chriſte for mercye / and by and by her doughter was made hole. Alſo Iob ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the / that the earthe is not onely full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy / but heauen and hell / for who hathe euer called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte for mercye / whiche hath not receiued it of him / ſo that he haue aſked it in faithe. And vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rours maieſte Charles the fyfte ſhal worke the Turke more ſorow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any prince hath done theſe .CCCC. yeres / ſo that thei whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che are vnder the ſigne of ſagittarius / ſhall preuayll and haue great victory / which ſhal be the Emperour hym ſelfe / or one of his bloude. And where I might here ſpeke mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the Emperours maieſte / and of diuers thinges / which ſhalbe done by him &amp; his no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles / let no man thinke the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary / but his actes ſhal excell and paſſe all other princes / 
<pb facs="tcp:7167:13"/> if he be not hindered by the perſwaſyons of the prelates of the Romayne empyre.<note place="margin">The ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye of Cibil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la cuma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na. Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande by thoſe letters / F E / A and G / the dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and the leap yeare. Math. xxiiij.</note> And to this dothe agree Cibilla Cumana / ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge owt of the ſpirite of prophecie / affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge it to chaunche betwixt F and E / A and G. Whiche prophecie endeth at .xlviij. yeares / or ſone after. Before that time the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſhall be great chaunge in the world / and ſtraunge wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders ſhalbe hearde of / that ſhal be trewe / althoughe thei ſhal apeare to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny / very vncredible. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more thingis ſhall chaunche in a verye ſhorte tyme / then hathe bene ſeene many yeares before. And the laſte ſigne and token after theſe / there ſhalbe ſo great perſecution and tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as hathe not bene ſeene nor hearde of / ſyns the beginning of the world. And after this perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſhall the ſonne be darkened / and the mone ſhall not geue her light / in ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that I do fynde eſpecially two fearefull Eclypſes of the moone / in ſo moch that ſhe ſhall loſe her lighte verye greatlye with in one yeare / and ſhalbe darkened from aboue to benethe / and theſe Eclipſis ſhal giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / a great admonition and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge. For the operation of bothe theſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clypſis / ſhall chaunche betweene the yeare xxxvij. and .xlviij. ſignifying to vs / ſo great
<pb facs="tcp:7167:14"/> trouble &amp; heauynes to chaunce vnto the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritualtie / that I wyll lett paſſe to name the houre and daye / referringe it vnto the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of the Lorde. And ſo farre as thys cirkell doth ſtretch / ſo farre ſhall ther great diſquietnes be.<note place="margin">Apoca. xiij.</note> So that I wolde men ſhuld note theſe two figures folowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>calipſe. The fyrſt is / I ſawe a beaſte ryſyng out of the ſea / hauing .vij. heades .x. hornes and vppon his hornes .x. crownes / &amp; vppon his heade the name of blaſphemy / by which beaſte I vnderſtande that vſurper of Gods lawes / &amp; wicked tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Antechriſte / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath moſt beaſtly lyued and taught the people moſt wycked and beaſtly doctryne / whiche hath drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnderneth his ſubieccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vij. the moſt nobleſt Realmes of the whole worlde / he that hathe cares / let hym heare. And I behelde an other beaſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge out of the earth / &amp; he had .ij. hornes lyke a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be / &amp; he ſpake as great thingis as dyd the firſt / and cauſed the people which dwelled in the earthe to worſhippe the firſte beaſte / whoſe deadly wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des was healed by him / let him that redeth vnderſtande. Theſe prophecies are bothe chaunced &amp; fulfylled / &amp; we truſte by the helpe of God / that theſe thingis ſhal be redreſſed by the Emperours mayeſtie / 
<pb facs="tcp:7167:14"/> Charles the .v. &amp; his aſſiſtentes. After this ſhall come a good tyme / for there ſhall be a newe reformacion / whiche ſhall continewe longe / ſo that the name of the great Turke ſhalbe no more hearde of. In this tyme ſhal other fearfull thinges be ſene in the ſonne / for vppon the ſecond wenſdaye after eaſter at .v. of the clocke in the mornynge / in the .xxvij. degree / the ſygne beynge in Aries. Ther ſhalbe ſoche darknes as hath not bene ſene in many yeres before / which ſignifieth that many princes &amp; kynges ſhal rule to ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in one realm.<note place="margin">Miche. iiij.</note> Then (ſaieth the ꝓphet) ſhall they make of theyr ſwerdes plowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhares / and ſythes of their ſpeares / &amp; euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ſyt vnder hys vynearde and fygge tree / ſo that one people ſhall not lyft vp his weapen agaynſt an other / nether ſhall they fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thens forthe learne to fyght.<note place="margin">Eſa. ij.</note> After that ſhall the blynde Iewes knowe by the decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racyon of the prophecies of Iacob / that the true Meſſyas hath bene borne longe &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeres agone / which thei vnto this daye / haue loked for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge.<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>Geneſ</abbr> lxxi.</note> Whiche ꝓphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie ſayeth thus: when meſſias ſhalbe borne then ſhalbe taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iewes their ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and crown / and thei ſhalbe ruled of the Romyſſhe Empyre: which ſo chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced after
<pb facs="tcp:7167:15"/> the death of Chriſt. And throughe Titus &amp; Veſpaſianus they were brought vnder the ſubiection of the Emperour of Rome. And nowe I truſte (through the goodnes of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God) that it ſhalbe aſwel declared vnto the Iewes / as it hath bene beleued of the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / that Meſſias is come alredy So that then (after the deſtructyon of the Turkes) they ſhalbe all conuerted vnto the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belefe / &amp; the Goſpel ſhalbe receaued with all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And this is the good will &amp; mynde / of the moſt redoubted Emperour and godly prince Charles / &amp; that not onely in worde / but alſo in harte &amp; dede. For thys purpoſe hath the almyghtie God ordeyned ſo many godly and excellent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth his gouuernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the pure and vndefyled worde of god might be preached and ſyncerely taught / thorow out all his landes / to the honoure of God &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde. Wherby it ſhal appeare (I truſte) to all his true ſubiectes / to cauſe them to take the more courage / to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encreaſe of vertue / and preſeruacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maieſtie. Bleſſed be that houre when this ſhal come to paſſe / and bleſſed be all they which ſhall aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſet forwarde theſe thinges before rehearced vnto all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons.
<pb facs="tcp:7167:15"/> For the whiche let vs all praye with one harte &amp; mynde / that this Gods honour and our ſaluacion maye be obteyned / peace encreaſed / and al conſciences quyeted. For the Lorde knoweth what creatures we be / ſayinge / We are but aſſhes / &amp; to aſſhes ſhal we retourne agayn / and as we brought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing into this worlde / ſo ſhall we cary no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing away with vs.<note place="margin">Gen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij Ezechi. xvij.</note> Here with I make an ende / and take my leaue / neuer more enten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng after this to ꝓnoſticate / but wil coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell all men in the ſteade of pronoſtications to imbreace Godes worde / which is able to ſaue youre ſowles / according to the ſayeng of the apoſtell.<note place="margin">Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. i.</note> And all though in this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / I ſpeake moſte ſpecially of thoſe thinges / whiche are lyke to chaunce (by the natural inclinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the planetes) in dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelande / yet were it good for all other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; realmes / here with to be admoniſſhed and take good heade / for where ſo euer the Lorde is moſt diſhonoured &amp; his word reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted / ther will he firſt ſtrike &amp; plage / and yf ther be any (as ꝑchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ther wyll be ſome) which wil ſaye (tuſh) this ꝓnoſticator is no wiſer then mad Marlyn &amp; ſoche other falſe and prophane fabelers / as he dothe here in alleage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his authors / wel / admit that
<pb facs="tcp:7167:16"/> bothe thei and I were liars (as in deade we are no other) yet is the Lord rightuous and trwe / whiche wyll ſmyte the worlde withe his ſtaffe and rodde / and with the breath of his mouth / he will deſtroy the wicked.<note place="margin">
                  <abbr>Geneſ</abbr> xlix</note> But here will ſome men peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture obiect and ſaye / that theſe great threates and plages of god before reherſed and ſpoken of by the prophetes / were prophecyed agaynſte the wicked and diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Iewes / agaynſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doma and Gomorra / agaynſt their princes preiſtes cyties and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres / which thinges were fulfilled many honderd yeares paſte / as at the deſtruction of Hieruſalem &amp; ſoche other. Well / agaynſt all ſoch that thus arro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly wyll reaſon agaynſte the Lorde / will he him ſelfe whette his ſwearde / bende his bowe / and make redy his arowes / to ſhoote at thoſe diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t people / which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinewe ſtill in their ſynnes with moche more abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer did theſe heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Iewes. And let no man thynke / that his ſwerde is any ſhorter at this tyme ageynſte them that wyll not repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te and ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / then it was in time paſte. For trwly / the ſynnes which raygne at this daye in the world / do greatly ꝓuoke the plages &amp; vengeaunce of god to come ſhortlye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. And thoughe
<pb facs="tcp:7167:16"/> owr gracious god be a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſufferyng god / yet at lengthe he puniſſheth / and that with great viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / accordinge to the ſayinge of the ꝓphet Naum / where he ſayth.<note place="margin">Nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i.</note> The Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de taketh ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpon his enemies / &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth diſpleaſure for his aduerſaries / the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is no power nor prince / that can withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the Lorde of hoſtes / for loke what he ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth / it is done / and what he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth / it ſtandeth faſte.<note place="margin">Pſalm. xxxij.</note> There is no counſell whiche ſhall lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge preuayle / if it be agaynſt the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / accordinge to the ſayinge of the prophet Dauid / ſpeakinge on this wiſe. The Lorde bringeth the counſell of the vnfaithfull to naught / and turneth the deuices of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / but the counſell of the Lorde endureth / and the thoughtes of his harte / fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A kynge is not holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he) by his owne great hooſte / nether is a Giau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaued throuh the might of his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſtreangth.<note place="margin">Pſalm xxxiij. Nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i.</note> Let vs now therfore feare the Lorde / for at the ſight of his diſpleaſure / all the worlde ſhall ſhake and tremble for feare who may abide his diſpleaſue / or ones flee from his indignacion? his anger taketh on like fire / ſo that the harde rockes (ſayeth the prophet) at his diſpleaſure braſte in ſonder.<note place="margin">Eſa. xi.</note> Therfore all trew and faithfull chriſtians / lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and morne / for the day of the lorde is
<pb facs="tcp:7167:17"/> at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth as a diſtroyer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the almighty.<note place="margin">Eſaye. xiij.</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal all ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des be lette<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down and all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hertes ſhal melte away / care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes &amp; ſorow ſhall come vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; their faces ſhal burne like the fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me / becauſe (ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ꝓphet) the day of the Lord ſhalbe ſo terrible / that his indignacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wrath ſhal be caſte vpon the face of thearth / to make it waſte / &amp; to root out the ſynne therof. Heare what the Lorde ſaieth / by the mouth of his ꝓphet / Wo be to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaieth he) that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnrightuous lawes / <note place="margin">Eſai. x.</note> deuiſinge thinges to harde to be kept / wherby the pore are op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſed on euery ſyde / and the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t people ar therwith robbed of iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / the widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es made a pray / ſo that the fathirles be ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led of their goodis.<note place="margin">Iob. xij</note> This may alme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee how the godly and innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be entreated and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed to ſcorne / and the houſes of robbers be in wealth and proſperite. The Lorde euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting / which hath the hertes of all kinges and princes in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / to turne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where euer he will / preſerue the Emperours moſt noble maieſte / with all kinges and princes and ſtabliſſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with great honour &amp; lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lyfe / to ꝓmote the goſpel of Chryſt. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Let euery man fear the day of the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / for it is harde at hande.</p> 
                  <bibl>Eſaye. xiij.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.xliij. in Maye.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
